Medway, Mass. The Community Church records, 1750-1978.
Congregational Library & Archives
Medway, Mass. The Community Church records, 1750-1978.
RG4685
Congregational Library & Archives
0.63 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes)
The Second Church of Christ was gathered on October 4, 1750. The church's first minister, David Thurston, was called on April 24, 1752. Construction on a new church building atop "Rabbit Hill" began in 1813 and construction was completed in 1814. In 1838, 31 members of the church were dismissed to form a sister church, the Village Church in Medway. Following a church controversy that resulted in excommunications and expulsions from the Second Church, the Third Church in Medway was formed. The two churches merged in 1902. In 1901, the Second Church of Christ was renamed to the Second Congregational Church. In 1940, the church federated with the local Baptist church to form The Community Church. In 1995, the Congregational, Baptist, and Community church bodies voted to formally unite as the Community Church of West Medway, also called the Medway Community Church. The church is still active today. The collection includes church and parish records, membership records, financial records, and ecclesiastical council records.
The Community Church (Medway, Mass.)
Second Church of Christ (Medway, Mass.)
Second Congregational Church (Medway, Mass.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Medway Community Church in April 2003 and November 2004; no accession number.
Historical Note
Owing to the growing population in the western portion of Medway, the West Medway Precinct was incorporated in 1748. Planning for the Second Church of Christ in Medway began shortly after with construction on a meeting house beginning on April 6, 1749. The Second Church of Christ was formally gathered on October 4, 1750. The church's first minister, David Thurston, was called on April 24, 1752. Due to health concerns, he asked for his dismissal from the church in 1769. The church remained without a minister until 1773 when David Sanford accepted the church's call. He continued to serve as the minister until his death in 1810.
Construction on a new church building atop "Rabbit Hill" began in 1813 and the building was dedicated on June 23, 1814. Jacob Ide was ordained and installed as the third minister of the Second Church on November 2, 1814. A Parish House was built between 1816 and 1817 and a Sunday school was established in 1819. In 1838, 31 members of the church were dismissed to form a sister church, the Village Church in Medway. The church building underwent a significant renovation in 1846. The church purchased a nearby home for use as a parsonage in 1872.
The Second Church experienced a significant controversy, beginning in 1881, which ultimately resulted in a split within the church and the formation of the Third Church in Medway. In 1881, Charles H. Deans, a prominent Republican political figure and trial justice, was accused of using his office to issue an arrest warrant for Nathan A. Williams out of personal spite, among other accusations of abuse of power, especially concerning the selective issuance of arrest warrants. His case was brought before the Governor's Executive Council and Deans was acquitted. However, the church council at the Second Church, found Deans guilty and subsequently excommunicated him. A group of church members disagreed with the excommunication and were also, subsequently, expelled. These expelled members went on to form the Third Church in Medway. They began meeting in 1884, though the church wasn't formally gathered until 1886. The Mendon Conference of Congregational Churches called an ecclesiastical council to intervene on behalf of those expelled, but the Second Church refused to admit any wrongdoing, or even to let the council use the meeting house for the ecclesiastical conference. The Second and Third Churches remained split until 1902 when the Second Church passed a resolution admitting to "unchristian" actions towards the members of the Third Church.
In 1901, the Second Church of Christ in Medway formally changed its name to the Second Congregational Church. The 1938 New England Hurricane destroyed the Baptist Church in Medway. The Second Church invited the Baptists to meet at their church building and in 1940, the two congregations formed a new federated church, The Community Church. Following the formation of the United Church of Christ in 1957, The Community Church decided to join the National Association of Congregational Christian Churches. An addition to the church building to house Sunday school classes was completed in 1970. The church building underwent a major renovation between 1980 and 1986.
In 1995, the Congregational, Baptist, and Community church bodies voted to formally unite as the Community Church of West Medway, also called the Medway Community Church. Also, in 1995, the church joined the Conservative Congregational Christian Conference. The church steeple was destroyed by fire in 2009 after being struck by lightning. A restoration of the building was completed in 2011. The church continues to serve the Medway community today.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains records related to The Community Church in Medway, as well as records related to the Third Church in Medway, which split away from the Second Congregational Church. The collection includes church and parish records, membership records, correspondence and communications, clippings, financial records, records related to ministers, and ecclesiastical council records.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged into the two series listed below. Materials within each series have been arranged by chronological order according to start date.
Series 1: The Community Church records, 1750-1978
Series 2: Third Congregational Church records, 1884-1902
Bibliography
Maxwell, Margaret. The Church on Rabbit Hill: A History of the West Medway Community Church. Medway: Snowfall Press, LLC., 2011.
Church controversies.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Excommunication.; Pews and pew rights.; Medway Community Church (Medway, Mass.); Second Church of Christ (Medway, Mass.); Second Congregational Church (Medway, Mass.); The Community Church (Medway, Mass.)
- The Community Church records, 1750 1978; 1750-1978; 2 Volume; 28 Folders
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains records related to The Community church in Medway, which was previously known as the Second Church in Medway. This series contains church and parish record books, records related to ministers, clippings, some financial records, printed copies of church manuals, confessions of faith, and covenants, and records related to the excommunication of Charles H. Deans.
  - Church records, 1750 1860; 1750-1860 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  - Confessions of faith, 1787 1827; 1787-1827 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Reciepts, 1790 1891; 1790-1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Pew deed facsimile, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Manuscript sermons, 1823 1832; 1823-1832 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Confession of faith and covenant, 1825 1848; 1825, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Petitions, 1843 1853; 1843-1853 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Parish records, 1845 1901; 1845-1901 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  - Parish warrants, 1847 1857; 1847-1857 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Financial reports, 1848 1863; 1848-1863 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - West Medway mirror and tea party times, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jacob Ide papers, 1853 1903; 1853-1903 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - David Sanford papers, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Anecdote regarding a sermon following Abraham Lincon's assassination, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Parish taxes, 1865 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Seth W. Segur installation, 1873 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dr. Emmons in his study poem, 1878 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - List of deacons, 1878 1901; 1878-1901 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Manual, 1879 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Charles H. Deans excommunication, 1881 1887; 1881-1887 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 1882 1886; 1882-1886 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Ecclesiastical council records, 1883 1886; 1883-1886 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - A statement of the Congregational Church of West Medway, Mass., 1884 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - James M. Bell resignation clipping, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Thanksgiving day proclamation, 1897 (Folder 5)
  - Austin Metcalf bequest, 1899 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - History timeline, circa 1978 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Early membership records, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - S. Knowlton papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Pew plan, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Third Congregational Church records, 1884 1902; 1884-1902; 9 Folders
  This series contains records related to the third church in Medway, which broke away from the Second church following a major controversy around the excommunication of Charles H. Deans. This series contains membership records, church and financial records, clippings, and legal records.
  - Third Church membership records, 1884 1990; 1884-1990 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Third Church financial records, 1884 1897; 1884-1897 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Communications between Second and Third Churches, 1884 1902; 1884-1902 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Legal records, 1886 (Folder 4)
  - Financial records, 1886 1890; 1886-1890 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Church records, 1886 1892; 1886-1892 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Third Congregational Church records, 1886 1902; 1886-1902 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Third Church communications, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)